const arr = [{"id":0,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 13-year-old female presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with on and off menorrhagia, bleeding gums, and petechial rashes. Her laboratory reports show the following results; Hb= 12.5 g/dl, platelet count= 350,000/mm3, activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)= 49s (normal: 29-40s). Which of the following could be the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombotic microangiopathy","bool":false}]},{"id":1,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Where are most of the body's iron reserves found?","answers":[{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Myoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false}]},{"id":2,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following is the best test for the diagnosis of malaria?","answers":[{"option":"Microbiological culture","bool":false},{"option":"Thick and thin film","bool":true},{"option":"Serologic test","bool":false},{"option":"Enzyme-linked immunoassay (ELISA) test","bool":false},{"option":"Pap smear","bool":false}]},{"id":3,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 13-year-old girl falls and hits her head on the wall, leading to trauma of the blood vessels. Tissue thromboplastin will be released by the endothelial cells. Which of the following factors will be involved in initiating coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"High-molecular-weight kininogen (HMWK)","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":true},{"option":"Factor IX","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V","bool":false},{"option":"Factor XII","bool":false}]},{"id":4,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following components are involved in the first step of heme synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Malonyl CoA and glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA and glycine","bool":true},{"option":"Malonyl CoA and serine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA and serine","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}]},{"id":5,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which antibody has a pentameric structure?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true}]},{"id":6,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 7-year-old boy developed vesicles and bullae on his face and arms due to prolonged sun exposure from participating in sports activities. His father had a similar condition. He is suspected of porphyria cutanea tarda. Which of the following enzymes is mainly deficient in the above-mentioned disease condition?","answers":[{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen carboxylase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen dehydratase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase","bool":true},{"option":"Uroporphyrinogen synthase","bool":false}]},{"id":7,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following is the region in the primary structure of immunoglobulins that determines the antibody class?","answers":[{"option":"Variable region of heavy chain","bool":false},{"option":"Constant region of heavy chain","bool":true},{"option":"Constant region of light chain","bool":false},{"option":"Hypervariable region of light chain","bool":false},{"option":"Variable region of light chain","bool":false}]},{"id":8,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"C-reactive protein, which is elevated in case of inflammation and infection, falls into the category of which of the following plasma proteins?","answers":[{"option":"Transport proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma enzymes","bool":false},{"option":"Oncotic proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Acute phase proteins","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting proteins","bool":false}]},{"id":9,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 55-year-old man was diagnosed with constrictive pericarditis, two years after suffering from trauma to the heart. When he died an autopsy was performed. The heart was encased in a thickened, fibrotic pericardium. The pericardium was attached to the heart by a stingy material that was difficult to remove. What type of inflammation did the patient have in his pericardium?","answers":[{"option":"Purulent","bool":false},{"option":"Catarrhal","bool":false},{"option":"Serous","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":true},{"option":"Ulcerative","bool":false}]},{"id":10,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 65-year-old woman is being treated for pain and inflammation in her joints for the past year. Which of the following statements regarding the patient's inflammation is correct?","answers":[{"option":"It always follows the acute inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"It is predominantly characterized by a neutrophilic infiltrate","bool":false},{"option":"Abscess formation is the hallmark","bool":false},{"option":"It may result in granulomas composed of epithelial cells and blood vessels","bool":false},{"option":"It involves co-existence of inflammation, tissue repair and attempts at repair","bool":true}]},{"id":11,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"An individual sprains their ankle while hiking in the mountains and it becomes inflamed. Which of the following statements is most correct regarding this type of inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"It is characterized heat, redness, pain and swelling","bool":true},{"option":"It resolves within twenty-four hours","bool":false},{"option":"The cellular infiltrate comprises of macrophages and lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"It is not associated with tissue damage","bool":false},{"option":"It is characterized by the formation of granulomas","bool":false}]},{"id":12,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"The blood remains in circulation because of a balance between procoagulant and anticoagulant forces. Proteolytic destruction of which of the following by the protein C inhibits the process of coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"Activated factor VII and factor X","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor V and factor VIII","bool":true},{"option":"Activated factor I and factor IV","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor X and factor XI","bool":false},{"option":"Activated factor II and factor III","bool":false}]},{"id":13,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following terms best describes the occurrence of a disease in a community or region with a frequency clearly in excess of normal expectancy?","answers":[{"option":"Sporadic","bool":false},{"option":"Endemic","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemic","bool":true},{"option":"Exotic","bool":false},{"option":"Pandemic","bool":false}]},{"id":14,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following terms best describes the disease causation model that can be used for explaining the mechanism of chronic disease occurrence like diabetes and heart disease with multiple risk factors?","answers":[{"option":"Wheel of causation","bool":false},{"option":"Epidemiological triangle","bool":false},{"option":"Web of causation","bool":true},{"option":"Determinants of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Dynamics of disease transmission","bool":false}]},{"id":15,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"The complement system is a system of about 20 different proteins which perform important defensive functions in the body. there are three pathways of complement activation, classical pathway, alternate pathway, and mannose-binding lecithin pathway. These pathways merge at which of the following stages?","answers":[{"option":"Activation of C5a","bool":false},{"option":"Breakdown of C1","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C3b","bool":true},{"option":"Formation of the membrane attack complex (MAC)","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C7","bool":false}]},{"id":16,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 45-year-old woman develops swelling in her lower legs and feet after standing for long periods at the end of her 8-hour shift with no associated pain or erythema. There is no swelling at the beginning of her day. Her kidney and liver are also in healthy condition. What is the probable diagnosis for her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Increased hydrostatic pressure due to heart failure","bool":true},{"option":"Gout","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Renal insufficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Arthritis","bool":false}]},{"id":17,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which is the characteristic morphology of red blood cells seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Macro-ovalocyte","bool":true},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Central pallor","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle-shaped red blood cells","bool":false}]},{"id":18,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which is the characteristic morphology of white blood cells seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Polymorphonuclear neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilic stippling","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Megaovalocyte","bool":false}]},{"id":19,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A child gets a micro-cut on his finger while playing with a razor. The wound stops bleeding shortly after. Which of the following mechanisms is primarily responsible for this?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrin formation","bool":false},{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Extrinsic pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet plug formation","bool":true},{"option":"Intrinsic pathway","bool":false}]},{"id":20,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"If the set point for diabetes mellitus in a population was 105 mg/dL and the researcher dropped it to 100 mg/dL. What will be the change in sensitivity and specificity?","answers":[{"option":"Sensitivity increases but specificity decreases","bool":true},{"option":"Only sensitivity increases","bool":false},{"option":"Sensitivity decreases but specificity increases","bool":false},{"option":"No change in sensitivity or specificity","bool":false},{"option":"Only sensitivity decreases","bool":false}]},{"id":21,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which one of the following types of cells starts their existence in the bone marrow, and gives rise to all blood cells on its own?","answers":[{"option":"Colony-forming unit-blast","bool":false},{"option":"Pluripotent hematopoietic stem cell","bool":true},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-erythrocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":22,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Why is blood classified as a special connective tissue?","answers":[{"option":"It consists of only fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It has a greater ratio of cells than fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It consists of hydroxyapatite crystals in its matrix","bool":false},{"option":"It is composed of cells and fibers","bool":false},{"option":"It has fluid nature of its ground substance","bool":true}]},{"id":23,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which one of the following is an unencapsulated lymphatic tissue found in the human body?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Tonsils","bool":false},{"option":"Peyer patches","bool":true},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false}]},{"id":24,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"In comparison to primitive hematopoiesis, which of the following is not the feature of definitive hematopoiesis (DH)?","answers":[{"option":"During definitive hematopoiesis, many types of white blood cells are produced","bool":false},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis is permanent","bool":false},{"option":"During definitive hematopoiesis, red blood cells do not have the nuclei","bool":true},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis starts in yolk sac","bool":false},{"option":"Definitive hematopoiesis begins in fetal life","bool":false}]},{"id":25,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A biopsy specimen of the thymus from an old man is examined under the microscope and many whorl-like corpuscles are observed. Which of the following statement truly matches the corpuscles mentioned above?","answers":[{"option":"They are mainly located in the thymic cortex","bool":false},{"option":"They have their embryological origin from mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"They are derived from T memory cells","bool":false},{"option":"They are frequently seen in thymus of young individuals","bool":false},{"option":"They are composed of epithelial reticular cells (type VI)","bool":true}]},{"id":26,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following proteins stimulates the expansion and multiplication of nearly all types of stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3 (IL-3)","bool":true},{"option":"Interleukin-6 (IL-6)","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophage colony-stimulating factor (M-CSF)","bool":false}]},{"id":27,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following cells does erythropoietin stimulate to enhance RBC synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Pluripotent hematopoietic stem cell (PHSC)","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyles","bool":false},{"option":"Colony-forming unit-erythrocytes (CFU-E)","bool":true},{"option":"Basophil erythroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Proerythroblast","bool":false}]},{"id":28,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following have MHC-I molecules present on their surfaces?","answers":[{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Coreceptors","bool":false},{"option":"T cell antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Processed foreign antigens","bool":false},{"option":"Processed self-antigens","bool":true}]},{"id":29,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A middle-aged obese doctor presents to the emergency room with complaints of significant left-sided chest \"tightness\" and pain that radiates to his left arm and jaw. He was given streptokinase when he was diagnosed with a heart attack four months back. The patient went into shock after receiving a fibrinolytic drug due to a hypersensitivity reaction. Which fibrinolytic agent did the patient receive this time?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Retaplase","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":false}]},{"id":30,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following terms denotes the average weight of hemoglobin in an individual erythrocyte?","answers":[{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH)","bool":true},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC)","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular volume (MCV)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin index","bool":false},{"option":"Hematocrit","bool":false}]},{"id":31,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 40-year-old man was recovered after having walked for hours, two days after becoming lost in a sweltering and humid wilderness. His complete blood picture showed increased hematocrit. Which of the following is a likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Primary polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Relative polycythemia","bool":true},{"option":"Physiological polycythemia","bool":false}]},{"id":32,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"The hematocrit of a person with a tumor-like disease is elevated. What value of hematocrit value would you most likely expect to see?","answers":[{"option":"More than 70%","bool":false},{"option":"More than 50%","bool":true},{"option":"Less than 30%","bool":false},{"option":"10% above normal","bool":false},{"option":"80% above normal","bool":false}]},{"id":33,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which one of the following values corresponds to the percentage of hemoglobin A2 (HbA₂) in a normal adult person?","answers":[{"option":"2.5 to 3.5%","bool":true},{"option":"0.5 to 0.8%","bool":false},{"option":"0.9 to 1.4%","bool":false},{"option":"4.5 to 5.5%","bool":false},{"option":"1.5 to 1.9%","bool":false}]},{"id":34,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 44-year-old man discovers he is positive for HIV after a blood donation screening. The screening of blood work shows hemoglobin of 10 g/dL, hematocrit 30%, total leukocyte count 4600/mm³, platelet count 15,000/mm³, prothrombin time 12 seconds (INR=1.1), and partial thromboplastin time 23 seconds. Which physical finding is most likely in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Subungual hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Deep venous thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":true},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Visceral hematoma","bool":false}]},{"id":35,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 44-year-old man is treated with high doses of rabbit anti-thymocyte globulin for bone marrow failure. He develops fever, lymphadenopathy, arthralgias, and erythema of the hands and feet arise ten days later. Which of the following is the most probable explanation for these signs and symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Polyclonal T-lymphocyte activation","bool":false},{"option":"Cytokine secretion by natural killer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophil degranulation","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complex deposition in tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Widespread apoptosis of B lymphocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":36,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 20-year-old lady visits the doctor, after five years of significant menstrual bleeding. She complains of easy bruising and states that bleeding from a tiny finger cut lasts longer than normal. Lab results show a hemoglobin of 10.5g/dL, and a platelet count of 275,000/mm^3, with normal platelet aggregation. Prothrombin time is 10.5 seconds (INR = 1.0) and аctivated partial thromboplastin time is 28 sec. Pap smear shows no abnormalities. Which of the following hematologic disorders is the most likely cause of this patient's menorrhagia?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Afibrinogenemia","bool":false},{"option":"Intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false}]},{"id":37,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following features characterizes fetal hemoglobin compared to adult hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"It has delta polypeptide chain","bool":false},{"option":"It contains five pyrrole rings","bool":false},{"option":"It unloads oxygen to tissues with difficulty","bool":false},{"option":"It possesses more affinity for oxygen","bool":true},{"option":"It shows lesser oxygen content at a given partial pressure of oxygen","bool":false}]},{"id":38,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"After the breakdown of red blood cells, which of the following proteins binds hemoglobin to be cleared by liver macrophages?","answers":[{"option":"Hemopexin","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemin","bool":false}]},{"id":39,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 5-year-old child was brought to a clinic with complaints of high-grade fever, pain in the throat, and difficulty in swallowing. Examination and a blood test confirmed the diagnosis of acute bacterial infection of the tonsils. Which of the following cells would be increased in blood in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}]},{"id":40,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 68-year-old male with carcinoma of the lung was given subcutaneous heparin to prevent any intravascular coagulation. The activity of this anticoagulant is increased when it combines with a protein. Which one of the following proteins shows this effect?","answers":[{"option":"Protein C","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombomodulin","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":true},{"option":"Protein S","bool":false}]},{"id":41,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A young woman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of being exhausted and short of breath when she tries to do anything. She has a respiratory rate of 18 breaths per minute and is quite pale. Hemoglobin is 10 g/dL according to the lab results. What is the approximate amount of oxygen that is transported by each one hundred milliliters of her blood?","answers":[{"option":"15 mL","bool":false},{"option":"20 mL","bool":false},{"option":"10 mL","bool":false},{"option":"8 mL","bool":false},{"option":"13 mL","bool":true}]},{"id":42,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 65-year-old woman arrives at the orthopedic department with joint pain. Her doctor diagnoses her with osteoarthritis and osteoporosis. She is prescribed NSAIDs, calcium, and vitamin D. She returns after six months on the same medication, pale and short of breath. Her MCV is 73 fL and her hemoglobin was 9 g/dL. What could be the cause of low hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false}]},{"id":43,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 24-year-old Indian male arrives at the emergency room with severe chest and back pain that started three hours earlier while he was ascending a mountain and was short of breath. He states that he experienced identical symptoms several years earlier. Lab tests show that hemoglobin is 10 g/dL, total leukocyte count is 12,000/mm3, MCV is 87 fL, and reticulocytes are 25%. What could be his diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true}]},{"id":44,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A manufacturing company worker who looks sick, feverish, and tired, complains of bleeding from the nose and gums. The laboratory findings show that the patient has low levels of hemoglobin, white blood cells, and platelets, as well as a low reticulocyte count and a mean corpuscular volume of 88 fL. What could be the potential diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false}]},{"id":45,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 27-year-old Ethiopian male presents to the outpatient department with breathlessness. He has a high heart rate and pale oral mucosa and conjunctiva. His initial blood tests showed 7.8 g/dL hemoglobin and 65 fL MCV. The doctor advises iron studies, which are normal. What could be the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":46,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 24-year-old media sciences student presents with exhaustion, nausea, and vomiting for one week. She also has a low-grade fever and visited the outpatient department after observing yellow skin and sclera. Abdominal examination reveals right upper abdominal discomfort. Her liver tests are abnormal. She is diagnosed with hepatitis A after testing. Which immunity will she build from her acute viral infection?","answers":[{"option":"Innate immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural passive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Artificial passive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Natural active immunity","bool":true},{"option":"Artificial active immunity","bool":false}]},{"id":47,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A young man presented to the outpatient department with complaints of fever for 5 days and body aches. He has stable blood pressure, 103° C temperature, 110 beats/min pulse, and 20 breaths/min respiration. His total leukocyte count was 2500/μL. Which reflects his condition best?","answers":[{"option":"Leukemoid reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Leukoplakia","bool":false}]},{"id":48,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Elevated concentration of lactate in the plasma is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin D deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Myocardial infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Exercise-induced muscle fatigue","bool":true},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":49,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"When interpreting an iron profile, which of the following parameters is the most reliable indicator of iron deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Serum hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin levels","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron levels","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron-binding capacity","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false}]},{"id":50,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following is the first bile pigment produced in the catabolism of heme molecule?","answers":[{"option":"Cholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Deoxycholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Biliverdin","bool":true},{"option":"Lithocholic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Bilirubin","bool":false}]},{"id":51,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What is the net yield of ATP molecules produced by the glycolysis of one glucose molecule in red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"36 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"0 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"6 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"2 ATP","bool":true},{"option":"1 ATP","bool":false}]},{"id":52,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which form of vitamin K is required for the activation of clotting factors?","answers":[{"option":"Menaquinone","bool":false},{"option":"Menadione","bool":false},{"option":"Dimenadione","bool":false},{"option":"Phylloquinone","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroquinone","bool":true}]},{"id":53,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"The plasma proteins electrophoresis shows two major protein electrophoretic bands, one for albumin and the other for globulin. Globulin further gives different fractions. These are α1 globulins, α2 globulin, β1 globulin, β2 globulin, and γ globulins. Which of the following is the protein present in the γ globulin fraction?","answers":[{"option":"Acid glycoprotein","bool":false},{"option":"Immunoglobulins","bool":true},{"option":"Haptoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Ceruloplasmin","bool":false},{"option":"Transthyretin","bool":false}]},{"id":54,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What is the most characteristic feature of granulation tissue?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of monocytes and fibroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Resemblance to granuloma","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of neutrophils and macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Growth of fibroblasts and new capillaries","bool":true},{"option":"Presence of exudate","bool":false}]},{"id":55,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 41-year-old man comes into the medical outpatient department with complaints of weight loss, nausea, and vomiting for 5 months. He works at a factory that produces plastic pipes. On physical examination, he has tenderness to palpation in the right upper quadrant of the abdomen with hepatomegaly. An abdominal CT scan shows a 12 cm mass in the right lobe of the liver. A liver biopsy is performed, and a microscopic examination shows an angiosarcoma. The patient has most likely been exposed to which of the following agents?","answers":[{"option":"Benzene","bool":false},{"option":"Vinyl chloride","bool":true},{"option":"Beryllium","bool":false},{"option":"Asbestos","bool":false},{"option":"Arsenic","bool":false}]},{"id":56,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 25-year-old male patient visited the outpatient department with complaints of shortness of breath at rest. His chest is normal on auscultation and there are no visible signs of lung disease on X-ray. He has low hemoglobin and an MCV of 105 fL based on his blood tests. Multisegmented neutrophils are not seen on blood smear. What could be the cause of his anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Liver disease","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":57,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"An 18-year-old male comes to the outpatient department with a palpable mass on the right side of his neck for 6 months. On physical examination, there is a 2 cm, firm, non-tender nodule involving the right lobe of the thyroid gland. Biopsy specimens of the nodule showed features consistent with carcinoma of the thyroid. No positive family history was found. Which of the following is relevant in the woman's past medical history?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic alcoholism","bool":false},{"option":"Exposure to arsenic compounds","bool":false},{"option":"Blunt trauma from a fall","bool":false},{"option":"Radiation therapy in childhood","bool":true},{"option":"Ataxia telangiectasia","bool":false}]},{"id":58,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 52-year-old man noted a darkly pigmented \"mole\" on the back of his hand. During the past month, the lesion has gradually enlarged and bled spontaneously. On examination, there is a slightly raised, darkly pigmented, 1.2 cm lesion on the dorsum of the right hand. The lesion is completely excised. Microscopically, malignant melanoma is diagnosed. Which of the following factors is associated with the greatest risk for the development of this neoplasm?","answers":[{"option":"Smoking tobacco","bool":false},{"option":"Ultraviolet radiation","bool":true},{"option":"Asbestos exposure","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Allergy to latex","bool":false}]},{"id":59,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 58-year-old woman experienced an increased feeling of fullness in the neck for the past 3 months and noted a 3 kg weight loss during that time. On physical examination, there is a firm, fixed mass in a 3 × 5 cm area on the right side of the neck. A biopsy of the mass is performed. All areas of the tumor have similar morphology. Which of the following terms best describes this neoplasm?","answers":[{"option":"Adenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Leiomyoma","bool":false},{"option":"Well-differentiated adenocarcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Anaplastic carcinoma","bool":true},{"option":"Squamous cell carcinoma","bool":false}]},{"id":60,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Malignant neoplasms can be categorized as carcinomas and sarcomas. Which of the following statements describes carcinoma?","answers":[{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of mesodermal origin","bool":false},{"option":"Arising from sheets of solid mesenchyme","bool":false},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of ectodermal origin","bool":false},{"option":"Arising exclusively from the cells of endodermal origin","bool":false}]},{"id":61,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 26-year-old woman has a lump in her left breast. On physical examination, the physician finds an irregular, firm, 2 cm mass in the upper inner quadrant of the breast. A fine-needle aspirate of the mass shows carcinoma. The patient's 30-year-old sister was recently diagnosed with ovarian cancer, and 3 years ago her maternal aunt was diagnosed with ductal carcinoma of the breast and had a mastectomy. Which of the following genes is most likely to have undergone mutation to produce these findings","answers":[{"option":"ERBB2 (growth factor receptor gene)","bool":false},{"option":"BCL2 (anti-apoptosis gene)","bool":false},{"option":"BRCA1 (DNA repair gene)","bool":true},{"option":"HSTI (fibroblast growth factor gene)","bool":false},{"option":"EGF (epidermal growth factor gene)","bool":false}]},{"id":62,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A first-year medical student develops pneumonia and is in the hospital for a week. Two weeks after hospital discharge, he develops a fever and begins coughing up thick, whitish, foul-smelling sputum. Computed tomography (CT) scan chest shows a localized collection of thick fluid in the lung. How would you best describe the outcome of acute inflammation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Resolution","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Abscess formation","bool":true},{"option":"Granuloma formation","bool":false},{"option":"Ulcer formation","bool":false}]},{"id":63,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What term best describes the type of inflammation in a 4-year-old child with redness and blister formation on the hands after accidental contact with boiling water?","answers":[{"option":"Serous","bool":true},{"option":"Suppurative","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":false},{"option":"Granulomatous","bool":false},{"option":"Ulcerative","bool":false}]},{"id":64,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which statement best describes autosomal dominant disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Protein shows loss of function","bool":false},{"option":"New mutations detected early clinically","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced penetrance and variable expressivity","bool":true},{"option":"Onset usually early in life","bool":false},{"option":"Disease in homozygous state","bool":false}]},{"id":65,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"An affected male does not transmit the disorder to his sons, but all daughters are carriers. Which pattern of inheritance corresponds to the above statement?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Sex chromosome abnormality","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false}]},{"id":66,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which cell type is most likely to be increased in a first year medical student experiencing excessive sneezing and watering of the eyes every year during spring and summer?","answers":[{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}]},{"id":67,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 34-year-old man complains of epigastric pain. Endoscopy reveals a shallow sharply demarcated ulcer in the gastric antrum. Biopsy findings include lymphocyte, macrophage, and plasma cell infiltration, along with granulation tissue formation and fibrosis. What term best describes the type of inflammation observed in this man?","answers":[{"option":"Acute","bool":false},{"option":"Serous","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinous","bool":false},{"option":"Granulomatous","bool":false}]},{"id":68,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What does the membrane attack complex (MAC) formed during complement activation consist of?","answers":[{"option":"C5b, C6, C7, C8, and C9","bool":true},{"option":"C1, C2, C4 and C6","bool":false},{"option":"C5a and C5b","bool":false},{"option":"C1, C3b, and C4b","bool":false},{"option":"C3a, C3b, and C5b","bool":false}]},{"id":69,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What initiates the classical pathway of complement activation?","answers":[{"option":"Antigen-antibody complexes","bool":true},{"option":"Binding of mannose-binding lectin (MBL) to microbial surfaces","bool":false},{"option":"Breakdown of C3","bool":false},{"option":"Binding of C-reactive protein (CRP) to microbial surfaces","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of C3 convertase","bool":false}]},{"id":70,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the inflammation in a 65-year-old man with a 5-year history of osteoarthritis?","answers":[{"option":"Cytokines and growth factors having no role in this type of inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Granuloma formation as a constant feature in these patients","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophilic exudate with pus formation on biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Alternatively activated macrophages promoting tissue repair","bool":true},{"option":"Plasma cells and B lymphocytes being almost never found","bool":false}]},{"id":71,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Complement deficiencies lead to an increased risk of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Allergic reactions","bool":false},{"option":"Hypergammaglobulinemia","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial infections","bool":true}]},{"id":72,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What is the involvement of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC)?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle contraction","bool":false},{"option":"Blood clotting","bool":false},{"option":"Neurotransmitter release","bool":false},{"option":"Hormone regulation","bool":false},{"option":"Transplant rejection","bool":true}]},{"id":73,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"In a normal distribution curve, what percentage of the curve is represented by the shaded area under the curve with ±1 SD (plus minus one standard deviation around the mean) on either side of the mean value?","answers":[{"option":"45%","bool":false},{"option":"13%","bool":false},{"option":"68%","bool":true},{"option":"27%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":false}]},{"id":74,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What does sterilization refer to?","answers":[{"option":"Reducing the number of microorganisms to a safe level","bool":false},{"option":"Removing visible dirt from a surface","bool":false},{"option":"Killing or removing all forms of microbial life","bool":true},{"option":"Killing bacteria but not viruses","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivating viruses on a surface","bool":false}]},{"id":75,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What is the most resistant form of microbial life to physical and chemical agents?","answers":[{"option":"Viruses","bool":false},{"option":"Gram-negative bacteria","bool":false},{"option":"Fungal spores","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial endospores","bool":true},{"option":"Protozoan cysts","bool":false}]},{"id":76,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"What do agents referred to as \"bactericidal\" do?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibit bacterial growth","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivate bacterial toxins","bool":false},{"option":"Remove bacteria from the surface","bool":false},{"option":"Kill bacteria","bool":true},{"option":"Prevent bacterial attachment","bool":false}]},{"id":77,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 19-year-old woman came into the medical outpatient department with a history of frequent nosebleeds and increased menstrual flow. On physical examination, petechiae and purpura are present on the skin of her extremities. Laboratory studies show normal partial thromboplastin time (APTT), prothrombin time (PT), platelet count, and decreased von Willebrand factor activity. This patient most likely has a derangement in which of the following steps in hemostasis?","answers":[{"option":"Vasoconstriction","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet adhesion","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin generation","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet aggregation","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombin inhibition","bool":false}]},{"id":78,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 23-year-old pregnant woman has macrocytic anemia, an increased serum concentration of transferrin, and a normal serum concentration of vitamin B12. The most likely cause of her anemia is a deficiency of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Intrinsic factor","bool":false},{"option":"Cobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false}]},{"id":79,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 20-year-old woman presents to her primary care physician with heavy menstrual bleeding. Her physician prescribes tranexamic acid. What is tranexamic acid's mechanism of action?","answers":[{"option":"Activates plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Blocks cyclooxygenase","bool":false},{"option":"Activates platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Suppresses LH surge","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibits plasmin","bool":true}]},{"id":80,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A medical study is conducted to estimate the prevalence of hypertension amongst a defined population and evaluate people of different ages, ethnicities, geographical locations, and social backgrounds. Which one of the following options best describes the type of study design most appropriate for the above study?","answers":[{"option":"Correlational","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false},{"option":"Case-series","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":true},{"option":"Case-control","bool":false}]},{"id":81,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"In a study that began in 2001, a group of 3500 adults in Islamabad were asked about\r\nalcohol consumption. The occurrence of cases of liver cancer between 2018-2023 was\r\nstudied in this group. What is the above study design?","answers":[{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":true},{"option":"Correlational","bool":false},{"option":"Case-control","bool":false}]},{"id":82,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A research paper states that: \"To access the frequency of mood disorders among medical students of Karachi.\" Which of the following best describes the statement in the above scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Operational definitions","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Rationale","bool":false},{"option":"Topic","bool":false},{"option":"Objective","bool":true}]},{"id":83,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"In a small study, 12 women with ovarian cancer and 12 women with no apparent disease were asked whether they had ever used estrogen. Each woman with cancer was matched by age, race, weight, and parity to a woman without disease. Identify the study design.","answers":[{"option":"Case-control","bool":true},{"option":"Case report","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":false},{"option":"Ecological","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false}]},{"id":84,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"\"Like cases should be treated as like, and the benefits and the risks associated with research must be allocated equitably across patients.\" Which of the following best expresses this principle of medical ethics?","answers":[{"option":"Autonomy","bool":false},{"option":"Beneficence","bool":false},{"option":"Justice","bool":true},{"option":"Equality","bool":false},{"option":"Non-maleficence","bool":false}]},{"id":85,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A group of medical students started researching the health issues and quality of life of commercial sex workers. For data collection, they would have to go to various unsuitable places. They spent a year trying to collect data but enrolled a dozen participants. They became discouraged and left the study altogether. Which of the following options best describes the factor ignored by the students while deciding the research topic?","answers":[{"option":"Economics","bool":false},{"option":"Preventability","bool":false},{"option":"Feasibility","bool":true},{"option":"Magnitude","bool":false},{"option":"Politics","bool":false}]},{"id":86,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A researcher of a new drug trial informed the volunteers about the possible benefits of a new drug under trial in that study. She deliberately laid more emphasis on the possible benefits of the drug under trial and avoided discussion of the possible adverse effects of the drug to enrolled participants to increase participation. Which of the following identifies the central ethical principle lacking in the above scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Beneficence","bool":false},{"option":"Justice","bool":false},{"option":"Non-maleficence","bool":true},{"option":"Informed consent","bool":false},{"option":"Confidentiality","bool":false}]},{"id":87,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 25-year-old male patient presents with a history of irrelevant talks, anger, and suspicion towards family members, had a big fight with the family, and injured the younger with an iron rod. He has been brought to you for treatment. Which of the following would you consider before initiating an interview with him?","answers":[{"option":"Inquire about any danger objects with the patient","bool":true},{"option":"Ask the staff to hold the patient and sedate him immediately","bool":false},{"option":"Talk to the family and ask them to leave the patient alone","bool":false},{"option":"Talk to the security guard and restraint the patient forcefully","bool":false},{"option":"Wait for the patient's violent reaction to happen in the ward","bool":false}]},{"id":88,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"During the case discussion in the ward, you noticed that the safety measures in place for your junior doctor, who is responsible for taking psychiatric history from a violent patient, are inadequate.  What would you advise your junior doctor?","answers":[{"option":"Safety is not important as compared to the patient's illness","bool":false},{"option":"Reassure your junior doctor and ask her to take a complete history","bool":false},{"option":"Ignore the family’s account of the patient and his violent acts","bool":false},{"option":"Postpone the interview until all safety measures have been ensured","bool":true},{"option":"Wait for 72 hours to take the history from the patient","bool":false}]},{"id":89,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 22-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with a complaint of swelling in the neck region for 10-12 days. He does not give any history of flu or sore throat. Physical examination revealed right anterior cervical lymph nodes, about 1.0 cm in size., soft, non-tender, and mobile i.e. not fixed. The spleen is also enlarged. There is no other positive finding. What should be the next step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph node biopsy","bool":true},{"option":"Reassure the patient and send him home","bool":false},{"option":"Antibiotics/antivirals","bool":false},{"option":"Observe the patient for 3-4 weeks","bool":false},{"option":"Send viral serology/VDRL/PCR","bool":false}]},{"id":90,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Hemostasis is the natural process that stops blood loss when an injury occurs. Which of the following bleeding manifestations or associations suggests secondary hemostatic disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Distensible skin and lax joints","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Bruising","bool":false},{"option":"Epistaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Mucocutaneous bleed","bool":false}]},{"id":91,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 65-year-old male presents with a 2 months history of fever, lethargy, and night\r\nsweats. On physical examination, he has palpable cervical and axillary lymph nodes. The spleen is palpable 2 cm below the left costal margin. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Viral fever","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Metastatic cancer","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":true}]},{"id":92,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"A 62-year-old woman complains of fatigue and numbness in her arms and legs for 1 month and takes thyroid replacement therapy for hypothyroidism. She has a long history of diarrhea on and off. A complete blood count (CBC) shows white blood cells (WBC) 3.8x10^9/L (normal: 4.0 to 11 x 10^9/L), hemoglobin (Hb) 8g/dL (normal: 12 to 16g/dL), hematocrit (Hct) 27 percent (normal: 36 to 46 percent), mean corpuscular volume (MCV) 120 fL (normal: 80 to 100fL), and platelets 115x109/L (normal: 150 to 400x10^9/L). She is diagnosed as a case of megaloblastic anemia with vitamin B12 deficiency. Which of the following autoantibodies is most likely present in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Antigliadin antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Antimitochondrial antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anticentromere antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-intrinsic factor antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Antismooth muscle antibodies","bool":false}]},{"id":93,"info":"1st-year/blood/2023","question":"Which of the following is a characteristic of megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow will be hypercellular","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron will be reduced","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte count will be increased","bool":false},{"option":"Serum vitamin B12 will be increased","bool":false},{"option":"TIBC will be increased","bool":false}]}]
export default arr